the reason why why you remind a person
would still be dependent
on the pleasure of the senses despite
knowing how little satisfaction they
provide and so on fundamentally they
don't really know where the problem is
so you you know that
the sense objects the the pleasures you
get from them are not satisfactory and
so on but you don't really extend
understand the extent of the sense
objects you don't really understand the
extent of the pleasure you're chasing
so in other words when you think about
the dissatisfactory nature of the sense
dissatisfactory nature of the sense
objects
that is not entirely accurate because if
it were entirely accurate you would then
also understand the peril of it and you
would lose any desire and zeal towards
it
so the problem with
people still being attracted to that
which they know does not um
result in in happiness and it's actually
doing them more harmed and good the
problem that people are still addicted
to the pleasures of the senses
is they don't see where that pleasure
begins they only see
they only see
what they're used to
seeing on the level of the sense objects
but there is more to that picture that
that it's left out because of which
uh the addiction is not uprooted
and uh that which is left out is your
own body it's pretty much the
relationship of your own mind with your
own body of you with your own body
so when people get attracted to the
sense objects they don't realize that
they have already accepted
the pleasure and the attraction of their
own body as the basis
for those sense objects further and
that's why the buddha said for as long
as one one's mind is not developed in
regard to its own body
the desire to essentiality will be there
so
you have to start you have to be uh you
have to like when there is the the
central pull towards sense objects or
for the pleasure of it
at the same time your body
your senses are there peripherally
enduring as a basis from which you are
pressured so it's the relationship on that
so it's the relationship on that
peripheral level
between you
and that body that it's pressuring you
towards sense objects that's what needs
to be understood
and the reason why that's so hard to
understand or it takes a lot of effort
to understand is because the the body
the as a unity of your sense organs
does not appear cannot appear on the
level of your sense objects so your
dependence on the pleasures of the sense
objects is actually determined and and
dependent upon the pressure that your
own body exerts on your mind
so that's the whole uh similes we gave
in the past of you know taming an
elephant of damien a bull um it's like
um it's a wild animal
that you are tied to inseparable from your
you are tied to inseparable from your
mind
and uh that wants to go left and right
and eat this and not eat that and avoid
this and it will pressure you uh until
he gets what he wants
so the question is not about removing
the the agreeable and enticing things
from the world to be free the question
is about taming that which pressures you
because of which you're not free
so that's why a person is still
attracted to the sense objects despite
knowing how little uh satisfaction sense
objects provide because that's the
knowledge is limited the knowledge of oh
this is dissatisfactory is pretty much
only within the sense objects failing to
see this whole kind of
underlying pressure of your own body and
the pleasure you depend on on the level
of the body failing to see this wild
animal underneath
so they don't see that as a problem they
only think these sense objects that i i
may i become obsessed about that's where
the problem is now that's pretty much
the end result of the problem already
being there and uh
fully controlling you
so that's why yes the sense restraint
and not engaging with those sense
objects that are inciting of last and so
on is the prerequisite
and then you get to see really the roots
of the problem which is pretty much
the the body
the the senses that crave the pleasure
that they're used to that's it
so if you don't uh engage with the
pleasures that they're used to that the
used to part will fade away
uh their dependence on that will will
cease because they haven't been engaging
with it so that's like the
uh
if if if the animal is engaged in a
perpetually wild behavior
it's going to become used to that and
that will be its norm there will be its
measure there will be its need
but if then the animal is not allowed to
engage with these sites and smell test
touches they would be making its mind
wild and so on
it will calm down whether you want to
come down or not it will come down
because things that are
uh
of the agitating nature things that are
of the perturbing nature are are now
things that uh the animal has not been
engaging with
so
if you want to uproot the dependence on
the pleasure of the sense objects you
pretty much have to uproot the
dependence of the pleasure of this body
the agreeability
uh the ownership
the um
not seeing it uh peripherally as a thing
that endures there on its own
uh with its own thirsts and hungers and
perceptions and so on
so you need to fully disown the body
but that can only be done on the level
of that correct peripheral recognition
of what the body is it cannot be done on
the level of observing the body with
your senses because see you're not
observing the body you're observing the
sense objects that require the body
and even if you're
like you know catching every moment and
every sensation that passes through the
body that's all on the level of sense
objects and that's why not none of that which is
and that's why not none of that which is
uh underneath it
which is that necessary requirement for
for perceiving the sense objects none of
that will be affected by by that
practice and by those efforts
um
again in the same sense an eye cannot
see itself and for as long as you
believe that you can you will be pretty
much engaged in in very futile attempts
engaged in in very futile attempts
of of accessing
the that which is inaccessible accessing
your senses on the level of sense
objects and that's a contradiction in terms
and that's a contradiction in terms
so you need to see the body on the level
of the senses so on the level of the
framework of the the world of the sense
objects fully purify the relationship
between you and that body that appears
peripherally that's present peripherally
that's present peripherally
while you are engaged with sense objects
or when you're engaged with sense
objects you know so for as long as you have
you know so for as long as you have
sight
eyes nose and so on
the world of the sense objects is there
and the body as the unity of the sense
the body as the unity of the sense
organs is peripheral to that
it's it's it's always it's it's um it's
always the background of that domain of
the sense objects
and that's where you need to see it
so it's not about examining this
individual organs and looking at it with
other sense organs
it's about understanding the sixth sense
base it's understanding the the body as that
it's understanding the the body as that
thing which is there that needs to be
tamed on the level of that peripheral
through not engaging with actual sense
objects that are pulling you
and then that pressure that that body
exerts over you
will diminish and and the clearer you
see it on that level that's revealed
through sense restraint by the way
uh the more you get used to it and the
more you get used to it the less
pressure you will be
and then
then
the body will be seen correctly and any
possibility of the pleasure to be
accessed to be experienced through that
body uh will not be something that will
uh will not be something that will
interest your mind because the mind
would see the extent of danger
if if he chooses to go down that rabbit
hole so um the first as a so just to sum up
so um the first as a so just to sum up
basically the first thing you want to do
is um
if you want to stop chasing the sense
pleasures is start to start practicing mindfulness
is start to start practicing mindfulness
of the body
correctly not as an observation
technique or watching sensations or
modern vipassanas or whatever but by
seeing it peripherally as an enduring
bag of bag of skin that contains the
sense organs that are attracted to the
various pleasures that they get in their
respective domains you want to learn how
to see the body for what it is as a
thing in the world on the level of
peripheral without needing to attend to
it directly
and you will get to see that if you have
been practicing sensory strength
sufficiently guiding of the sensors
sufficiently being moderately eating
watchfulness and dwelling in solitude
because company and the world it pretty
much requires your mind to be on the
level of sense objects
and if you have not been sufficiently
withdrawn from that
you will not you simply
there isn't enough space say like that
for you to step back to get to see this
body as as the thing that induced there
in the world as a basis for all the
sense objects and so on you will not be
able to see the relation between the two
and you will not be able to see the the
right order between the two
so through scent restraint moderation
eating and gutting on the sense those
and dwelling in solitude you get to
discern the body
as a thing on its own in in their bag of
skin with the sense of organs that have
its own
respective domains that they're
attracted to repel from and so on
and you will see then that the pleasure of
you will see then that the pleasure of
the sense objects actually begins it's
actually rooted and it remains on the
level of that peripheral body and those
sense organs they're the ones thirsting
after and craving for and so on
and now that you have been sufficiently
now that you have been sufficiently
withdrawn from it
uh
you can actually disown that whole
pressure in the pull of these individual
organs you can see them as individual
five individual animals that they gave
the simile of
you could see these oh these are the
wild animals that need training when
people are engaged and not withdrawn
sufficiently from the sense objects they
can't they see that only in abstraction
which means they don't see it
they don't see their organs as as an
independent entities that pretty much
have its own life and cravings and needs
that they
need to tame and control
so each time there is a pull from this
side sound smell taste to touch they are
the ones pulled by sights and smell
taste of touch they don't see anything
in between because those sense organs
those animals do not appear on the level
of sense objects that you are so used to
looking at and measuring existence by
so that's why the whole practice of
censorship and that correct mindfulness
that peripheral awareness we often talk
about it's that peripheral signs and
features of that body that exists on the
level around
around
that which you're attending at the
background of it
that's where the body is that's the
that's what the buddha meant by saying
knowing the body to the extent necessary
for the final knowledge that's the
measure of that extent
how familiar
with the phenomenon of the body you are
on the level of peripheral
how steady your mind is in discerning the
steady your mind is in discerning the
you know the presence of the body for
what it is on its own
without needing to attend to it directly
without needing to make it a sense
object and if you develop that extent
and if you develop that extent
sufficiently yeah there will be no more
you will not be underlined by lasting
craving and thirst of the individual
senses by not seeing the senses by being
on the level of sense objects that's how
you are underlined by all the assaults
underlying tendencies
they underline you because you go over
them so they become that which is under
you and it kind of directs you and
pushes you and controls you
so you want to develop your mind to the
extent necessary when you're not
underlined when you underline them
let's say like that that's in another
suit but it would have said another
arahan's mind he's not overwhelmed by
things by damas by by pressures by some
he's the one that overwhelms them and
that's what it's meant by by the order
establishing the right order seeing what
comes first seeing the body on the level
of the peripheral as that which is first
and not losing that context despite of
what comes on the individual basis or of
your attention and so on
so whatever you're attending to whatever
pressure there is desire for pleasure
and so on the order of
that's determined by your knowledge now
does not change you still see that
peripheral body is the necessary basis
for all of this that's happening and all
you need to do is ah if i protect the
order there will be no room to become
underlined by perverting the order by
last version of distraction practice
that sufficiently and and the
last aversion and distraction will
completely fade because they have not
been maintained
through the perversion of the order
that's why i understand in that suit
that sensuality in itself is the exact
perversion of the order
putting the sense object first and
everything else measured through that
as second and not seeing the body
peripherally the necessary basis of
sense organs peripherally the sixth
sense space peripherally for what it is
to the extent that it is as that which
is first the necessary container for
everything else appealing or
disagreeable in the world
so if you unpervert that perception
there is absolutely no room for for
lust to breed and expand and so on or
aversion or distraction
so that's it